Preliminary Guide to the Africa News Service (Durham, N.C.) Leroy T. Walker Africa News Service Archive, 1952-1998 and undated (bulk 1952-1994)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leroy T. Walker Africa News Service Archive 1952-1998 and undated (bulk 1952-1994)
Africa News Service (Durham, N.C.)
606.6 linear feet Extent: 439,500 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00017
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
One accession of the collection has usage restrictions. Contact a reference librarian for more information.
In addition, some of the materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Leroy T. Walker Africa News Service Archive was donated by Africa News Service to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1997-2001.
Historical Note
Africa News Service (ANS) is a non-profit U. S. news agency founded in 1973. It is a leading information source on Africa in the United States and works in partnership with African news agencies and periodicals to make available current and background materials on all aspects of African life, politics, and culture. Through its efforts, coverage of Africa has been more frequent, more substantive, and more accurate, filling a vital gap for policy makers, educators, journalists, diplomats, scientists, religious groups, development analysts, and business and labor leaders. Widely known for its periodical Africa News, the award winning ANS also prepares special articles and series for major newspapers and broadcast programs and provides behind-the-scenes consultation and briefing for news agencies and individual journalists. Keeping pace with innovative computer technologies, ANS shifted in 1993 from printed to electronic publication by establishing Africa News Online. Through this on-line service ANS engages in computerized news gathering and distribution and e-mail communications with reporters in Africa. This on-line service is distributed commercially by international vendors such as Lexis/Nexis and Financial Times Information and is on the World Wide Web at www.africanews.org.
ANS is located in Durham, N. C. and is led by a trio of Duke graduates: Executive Director Bertie Howard ('69), Executive Editor Tamela Hultman ('68), and President and Managing Editor Reed Kramer ('69). In 1996 ANS and Duke University embarked on two collaborative ventures, the Center for Africa and the Media (CAM) as well as the the LeRoy T. Walker Africa News Service Archive. CAM is a joint program with Duke University's African and African American Studies Program that will help develop curricular offerings and conduct scholarly research as well as initiate visits and international exchanges with journalists and media scholars.
Collection Overview
The LeRoy T. Walker Africa News Service Archive is an extensive resource file assembled by ANS over the course of two decades in support of its news gathering efforts about Africa-related issues and U. S. foreign policy towards Africa. The collection spans the years from approximately 1960 to 1995, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1978 through 1994. Newspaper clippings, magazine articles, press releases, newsletters, brochures, and reports comprise the collection. Much of the material is gathered from mainstream media sources and government documentation in the United States, Europe, Africa, and other parts of the world. In addition, the collection includes significant resources from alternative, minority, and special interest presses world-wide that may be difficult to locate elsewhere. The archive contains scarce and difficult-to-locate materials such as numerous publications produced by non-governmental organizations and grass-roots/community groups that are/were involved in efforts related to independence movements, economic development, and human rights issues in Africa.
The archive is arranged in several series that provide a perspective on African politics and development from almost every country in the world. The heart of the archives is comprised of files about each African country. There are also significant files on U.S. politics and foreign policy and the United Nations. As ANS is located in North Carolina, there was a specific effort to document the activities and interests of North Carolinians as related to African issues. The archive encompasses a wide range of topics including agriculture, children, economics, education, health, history, politics, peace negotiations, social conditions, war, wildlife, and women. There are files on individuals, media organizations, political and cultural groups, corporations, and lobbyists. The collection documents the movement for African independence and economic development in the latter half of the twentieth century.
The archive is named in honor of LeRoy T. Walker, long-time supporter and honorary chair of the ANS Board of Directors. Mr. Walker is president-emeritus of the U. S. Olympic Committee and chancellor-emeritus of North Carolina Central University. A past president of The Athletic Congress, he has had a multi-faceted career in sports, physical education and educational administration; he has received numerous honors and honorary degrees. He has coached U. S. Olympic teams and trained and coached many African and American athletes. In the 1960s he served as director of programming and training for Africa at the Peace Corps in Washington, D.C.
Also transferred with the archive is a large number of Africa-related books, periodicals, and other printed materials. These items are being integrated and cataloged as part of Perkins Library's holdings on Africa and are identified in the on-line catalog by the (corporate) author entry: Africa News Service (Durham, N.C.) Archives.
The addition (9450 items, dated 1952-1993 and undated, bulk 1952-ca. 1980, 18.20 linear feet) contains resource files, newspaper clippings and other media, and periodicals, books, and pamphlets on various topics pertaining to South Africa and Southern Africa (especially Rhodesia and Zimbabwe). Topics include labor, industry, the economy, and foreign trade with South Africa; social conditions in South Africa including the state of Indian South Africans; and student, Christian, and other political movements against apartheid, including the National Union of South African Students and the University Christian Movement. Also includes 3 black-and-white photographs, and 3 microfiche. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Collection of African and African-American Documentation. (01-156)
Notes On Arrangement And Folder Titles
The collection is retained as it was assembled by ANS. The files were collected over two decades by a variety of staff members and volunteers. As issues in Africa evolved, subject files were established, emphasized or de-emphasized, resulting in some overlap in focus and sometimes inconsistency in filing. Many of the folder titles include span dates; however, it is not unusual to find materials dated earlier or later. As noted previously, the collection spans the period of the 1960s through 1995. Some dates on the folder titles are noted with the prefix, "thru" or a dash, e.g., "-1977". This indicates that the materials in the files dated before and up to 1977. If there is a dash after the date, e.g., " 1983- ", this indicates the files date 1983 forward. The span dates on the container list sometimes differ from the dates on the folder title. In preparing the container list, student workers sometimes looked within the folder to determine the actual span dates and listed this information. Attempts were made by ANS staff to arrange materials chronologically within the folders. Over time with numerous people using and filing the materials, some of this arrangement within the folder may have been lost.
Sometimes within the folders there are white slips of paper with a bibliographic citation. This is an indication that there is a relevant article in a periodical. The periodical title is often noted by an acronym. A key to the list of acronyms can be found after the List of Series below. Most of the periodicals cited should be available in Duke University's Perkins Library in hard copy, microform, or electronically.
Occasionally there are files labelled with just the letter of the alphabet, preceding folders with information about a specific topic. Such files were established when there were only one or two articles about the subject and a separate folder was not yet warranted. For example in the series, "Persons," there is a file for each letter of the alphabet, preceding the files labelled by individuals' names. This indicates that the file contains materials on several people whose last name begins with that letter of the alphabet. There are a few terms used as folder titles that require some clarification.
"General" indicates there was not sufficient material on a subject to divide into categories. Therefore the file would include a range of topics. For example, "South Africa: Bantustans - General" would include a variety of information about Bantustans as a subject and specific Bantustans. Following "General" are files on specific Bantustans, e.g., "Ciskei," indicating that there was sufficient information about Ciskei to warrant its own folder.
Bibliography is not used in the traditional sense of a list of citations, but rather is a file that includes book announcements, book reviews, or other statements about a publication of interest. Such materials can also be found interfiled within a specific subject file.
Reference files included brochures, pamphlets, statistics, and maps providing background information about a subject, usually a country.
Diplomacy files are used only in the series, "Africa: Countries," and refers to pre-independence efforts to form a new country. These files would include information on negotiations with former colonial powers, the United Nations, and/or with neighboring African countries. After independence was achieved files were labelled under the title, "politics."
Foreign Relations and Foreign Policy were not always clearly distinguished during the filing process. However, foreign policy focuses more on establishing positions related to issues while foreign relations deal with the interaction between countries based on the foreign policy.
Key to Periodical Acronyms
AAN
Anti-Apartheid News
AANWR
African American News & World Report
AFAS
Afriqueasie
Af Bus
African Business
AFR
Africa
AV
Atlanta Voice
BBC
BBC Summary
BC
Bulawayo Chronicle
BOT. DN
Botswana Daily News
B. PAN
Black Panther Paper
B. SUN
Baltimore Sun
BW
Business Week
CSM
Christian Science Monitor
DD
Daily Dispatch (E. London)
DMH
Durham Morning Herald
D OBS LIB
Daily Observer of Liberia
DS
Durham Sun
DT
Daily Times (Nigeria)
DU. CHR
Duke University Chronicle
DW
Daily World
EAST
East Africa Standard
ECON
Economist
ETH. HLD
Ethiopian Herald
FBIS
Foreign Broadcast Information Service
FDL
Frontline
FM
Financial Mail
FT
Financial Times
GD (UK)
Guardian (UK)
GD (US)
Guardian (US)
GDN
Greensboro Daily News
GH. DG
Daily Graphic (Ghana)
GH. P.
Pioneer (Ghana)
GH. T
Ghanaian Times
HE
Human Items
JA
Jeune Afrique
J DE A
Journal de Angola
J1 OF C
Journal of Commerce
JS
Johannesburg Star
KST
Sunday Times (Kenya)
KT
Kenya Times
LA
Liberian Age
LAT
Los Angeles Times
LeM
Le Monde
ME
Middle East
M. GD
Manchester Guardian Weekly
MPR
MERIP Reports
MT
Militant
NAF
New African
NAK
Nation (Kenya)
NAT. C.
National Concord
NC. AN.
N. C. Anvil
NDS
Daily Star (Nigeria)
NEW LIB
New Liberian
N. HER
Nigerian Herald
NJ & G
Norfolk Journal & Guide
N. NIGE.
New Nigerian
NR
New Republic
NW
Newsweek
NYP
New York Post
NYT
New York Times
OBS
Observer
oob
off our backs
PH. B.
Philadelphia Bulletin
PH. I.
Philadelphia Inquirer
RDM
Rand Daily Mail
RFG
Rhodesian Financial Gazette
RNO
Raleigh News & Observer
RP
Rapport
SACT
Cape Times (S. Africa)
SAD
South African Digest
SAFG
South African Financial Gazette
SAR
Southern Africa Report
SAST
Sunday Times (Johannesburg)
SCR
Standard & Chartered Review
S. HER.
Sun Herald
SoAf
Southern Africa
SPL
Spotlight
S. POST
Sunday Post (S. Africa)
ST
Sunday Times (London)
StK
Standard (Kenya)
ST OF Z
Sunday Times of Zambia
S. TRIB.
Sunday Tribune
SWOBS
Swaziland Observer
TDN
Daily News (Tanzania)
Times K
Kenya Times
Times L
Times (London)
Times N
Nairobi Times
TM
Time
T OF Z
Times of Zambia
TRIB
Tribune
TSW
Times of Swaziland
TTP
To The Point
TTPI
To The Point International
UMR
United Methodist Reporter
USN
U. S. News & World Report
VV
Village Voice
WAD
Windhoek Advertisor
WAF
West Africa
WBW
World Business Weekly
WP
Washington Post
W. REV
Weekly Review
WS
Washington Star
WSJ
Wall Street Journal
WT
Washington Times
WW
Workers World
WWF
World Wildlife Fund News
ZDM
Zambia Daily Mail
ZWE
Weekender (Zambia)
Subject Headings
Walker, LeRoy T., 1918-; Africa News Service. Archives; Women -- Africa; Africa -- Civilization -- 20th century; Africa -- History -- 20th century; Africa -- Social conditions -- 1960-; Africa -- Economic conditions -- 1960-; Africa -- Politics and government -- 1960-; Africa -- Agriculture; Africa -- Foreign relations; Rhodesia and Nyasaland; Zimbabwe; Africa, Southern; United States -- Foreign relations -- Africa; Africa -- Social life and customs; Microfiche; Black-and-white photographs; John Hope Franklin Research Collection of African and African-American Documentation
Contents of Collection
- Africa (General)
  Files in this series contain information related to the continent of Africa as a whole. Subject areas cover broad topics including culture, economy, education, health, religion, and women.
  - Anthropology, 1975-1980, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Bibliography, through 1989, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Culture, 1973-1986, (8 folders) (Box 2)
    - Cinema/Theater, 1971-1985, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - FESTAC, FESPAC (Box 2)
    - Language, 1971-1980, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Literature, 1972-1995, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Music/Dance (Box 2)
  - Economy, through 1977, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Economy, 1978-1990, (8 folders) (Box 3)
    - African Economic Community, 1990- (Box 3)
    - African Development Bank, through 1992, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Agriculture, 1976-1982, (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - Agriculture, 1983-1989, (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - Locusts (Box 4)
      - RURCON (Box 4)
    - Aid, through 1993, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Banking and Currencies (Box 4)
    - Banking: BCCI in Africa (Box 4)
    - Communication (Box 4)
    - Debt, 1986-1989, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Development (Box 5)
      - 1979-1992, (5 folders) (Box 5)
      - Global Coalition for Africa: Africa Capacity Building Foundation (Box 5)
      - Human (see also World Development: Human) (Box 5)
    - Drought (Box 5)
      - 1984, 85; 86-, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Foreign Response-- 1984-1988, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Drug Trafficking, through 1994 (Box 5)
    - Energy, through 1984, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - Environment (Box 6)
      - 1978-1991, (3 folders) (Box 6)
      - Deserts, (see also Economy: Drought) (Box 6)
      - Forests (Box 6)
      - Toxic Waste Dumping (Box 6)
    - Fishing (Box 6)
    - Food, through 1988, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Foreign Investment (Box 6)
    - Foreign Investment: African Business Roundtable (Box 6)
    - Housing (Box 6)
    - Industry (Box 6)
    - Lome Convention (Box 6)
    - Migrant Workers (Box 6)
    - Minerals (Box 6)
  - Economy (Box 6)
    - NYT Annual Survey, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - OCAM (Box 7)
    - Oil, through 1986, (4 folders) (Box 7)
    - Private Enterprise (Box 7)
    - Radical Analyses (Box 7)
    - Tourism, thru 1983, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Trade (Box 7)
      - thru 1990, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Commodities, 1973-1990 (Box 7)
    - Transport, through 1981, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Water (Box 8)
    - Workers (Box 8)
      - Unions (Box 8)
  - Education (Box 8)
    - 1977-1985, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Literacy (Box 8)
    - Univ. & Student Polls, through 1976, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Foreign Relations (Box 8)
    - through 1989, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Afro-Arab, through 1976, 1983-1988, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - France in Africa (Box 8)
    - Iran/Africa Relations (Box 8)
    - Persian Gulf Response, 1990-1991, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - Economic Effects (Box 8)
      - Reparations to Africans in the Diaspora (Foreign Relations) (Box 8)
      - Response to Changes: 1990- (Foreign Relations) (Box 8)
  - Geography (Box 8)
  - Geography: Maps (Box 8)
  - Groups: Club of Dakar (Box 8)
  - Health (Box 9)
    - thru 1992, (11 folders) (Box 9)
    - AIDS, 1984-1989, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - AIDS (Box 10)
      - 1990-1994, (4 folders) (Box 10)
      - African Origins (Box 10)
      - Kemron (Box 10)
    - Ebola (Box 10)
    - Guinea Worm (Box 10)
    - Malaria, through 1991, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - River Blindness (Box 10)
    - TDR Newsletter (Box 10)
  - History, through 1980, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Legal System (Box 10)
  - Media, through 1981, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Media (Box 11)
    - 1982-1994, (3 folders) (Box 11)
    - All Africa Press Service, 1984-1985 (Box 11)
    - Pan-African News Agency, 1972-1994 (Box 11)
    - West Africa, 1980-1991 (Box 11)
  - Military (Box 11)
    - thru 1987, (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - Mercenaries, 1973-1990 (Box 11)
  - Politics (Box 11)
    - through 1986, (7 folders) (Box 11)
    - Africa Leadership Forum, 1988-1994 (Box 11)
    - Democracy Movements, 1990-1991 (Box 11)
    - Democracy Movements (Box 12)
    - 1992-1994, (3 folders) (Box 12)
      - "Africa Demos", 1990-1996 (Box 12)
    - Ex-Portuguese Colonies, 1968-1994 (Box 12)
    - Human Rights, through 1995, (2 folders) (Box 12)
      - African Human Rights Newsletter, 1991-1996 (Box 12)
    - National Boundaries, 1988-1995 (Box 12)
    - OAU, through 1977, (7 folders) (Box 12)
    - OAU, 1978-1993, (11 folders) (Box 13)
    - OAU (Box 14)
      - 1993- (Box 14)
      - Peacemaking Documents, 1993-1995 (Box 14)
      - Documents, through 1983 (Box 14)
    - Pan-African Congress (Box 14)
      - 1971-1994 (Box 14)
      - Documents, 1971-1974 (Box 14)
    - Posters, 1971-1975 (Box 14)
    - Socialism, 1963-1990 (Box 14)
  - Reference, 1967-1984 (Box 14)
  - Refugees, through 1986, (10 folders) (Box 14)
  - Religion (Box 14)
    - 1962-1993 (Box 14)
    - Christianity, pre-1978 (Box 14)
    - Christianity (Box 15)
      - 1979-1985, (5 folders) (Box 15)
      - Catholicism (Box 15)
      - Pope's Visits, through 1990, (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - Indigenous, 1977-1994 (Box 15)
    - Islam (Box 15)
    - Jehovah's Witnesses (Box 15)
    - Judaism (Box 15)
  - Science & Technology (Box 15)
  - Society (Box 16)
  - Society: Children (Box 16)
  - Society: Children, African Kora (Box 16)
  - Society: Ethnic Groups (Box 16)
  - Society: Touareg (Box 16)
  - Society: Population (Box 16)
  - Sports (Box 16)
    - through 1993, (10 folders) (Box 16)
    - Durham (Box 16)
  - Wildlife (Box 17)
    - 1970-1991, (7 folders) (Box 17)
    - Poaching, 1988-1991, (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Women, 1976-1988, (6 folders) (Box 17)
  - Women (Box 18)
    - 1980- (Box 18)
    - Female Circumcision, 1987-1994 (Box 18)
  - Youth (Box 18)
- Africa: Regions (Box 18)
  These files are organized for the geographical regions of Africa, e.g., Central Africa. The information focuses on areas of common concern or shared interests such as weather, agriculture, ethnic groups, or resources. For example: many of the files under Southern Africa deal with the peace process in Angola (Box 22 - 23), inasmuch as several countries were involved in this effort. It is useful to also check for related materials in the files under the appropriate individual country in the series, "Africa: Countries."
  - Botswana, Lesotho, Swaziland (Box 18)
    - Economy (Box 18)
  - Central Africa, through 1980, (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - East Africa (Box 18)
    - Burundi, Rwanda, Tanzania (Box 18)
    - Economy (Box 18)
      - through 1987, (11 folders) (Box 18)
      - Kagera, 1977-1984 (Box 19)
      - Transport, 1970-1990, (5 folders) (Box 19)
    - Politics, 1971-1990, (6 folders) (Box 19)
    - Refugees, 1971-1993 (Box 19)
  - Horn, 1973-1978, Jan.-Feb., (4 folders) (Box 19)
  - Horn (Box 20)
    - 1978, Mar.-1994, (7 folders) (Box 20)
    - Refugees, 1973-1992, (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Indian Ocean, 1970-1991, (5 folders) (Box 20)
  - North Africa, 1972-1985, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - North Africa (Box 21)
    - 1986-1992 (Box 21)
    - Economy, 1993-1994 (Box 21)
    - Maghreb Union, 1976-1992 (Box 21)
  - Sahara, 1976-1992, (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Sahel (Box 21)
    - Bibliography, 1979-1984 (Box 21)
    - Club du Sahel Newsletter, 1990-1997 (Box 21)
    - Economy, 1973-1995, (6 folders) (Box 21)
    - PPS Documents, 1980-1981 (Box 21)
  - Southern Africa (Box 21)
    - General, 1965-1976, Aug.-Sept., (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - Southern Africa (Box 22)
    - General, 1976-1994, (9 folders) (Box 22)
    - Angola/Namibia/S.A. Peace talks (Box 22)
      - 1988 (Box 22)
      - Brazzaville, (2 folders) (Box 22)
      - Cairo (Box 22)
      - Cape Verde (Box 23)
      - Geneva (Box 23)
      - New York (Box 23)
      - 1989-1991, (5 folders) (Box 23)
    - Bibliography, 1969-1995 (Box 23)
    - Economy (Box 23)
      - 1980-1994, (5 folders) (Box 23)
      - Drought, 1992 (Box 23)
      - SADCC, 1983-1995, (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - Southern Africa (Box 24)
    - Economy (Box 24)
      - Transport, 1980-1995 (Box 24)
    - Frontline States (Box 24)
    - Lisbon Conference, 1977-1982 (Box 24)
    - Reference, 1980-1994 (Box 24)
    - Refugees, 1978-1990 (Box 24)
  - West Africa (Box 24)
    - General (Box 24)
    - Economy (Box 24)
      - 1973-1995, (7 folders) (Box 24)
      - ECOWAS, 1978-1994 (Box 24)
      - Rivers (Mano, Niger, etc) (Box 24)
      - WARDA, 1978-1990 (Box 24)
    - Politics, 1972-1992 (Box 24)
    - Refugees, 1979-1984 (Box 24)
- Africa: Countries (Box 24)
  This is the heart of the collection and is arranged alphabetically by country. The subjects cover a broad range of topics from health, history, military, refugees and students, to specific events, conferences, and organizations. There are related materials in other series such as "Persons," which includes files on noted personalities involved in Africa-related concerns, and "U.S. Foreign Relations," which provides insight into the United States policy toward specific African countries.
  - Algeria (Box 24)
    - Bibliography, 1973-1989 (Box 25)
    - Culture, 1980-1993 (Box 25)
    - Economy (Box 25)
      - 1972-1994, (5 folders) (Box 25)
      - Migrant Labor, 1985 (Box 25)
      - Oil & Gas, 1972-1994, (4 folders) (Box 25)
      - Reference, 1975-1979 (Box 25)
    - Foreign Relations, 1971-1980, (5 folders) (Box 25)
    - Foreign Relations, 1981-1994, (4 folders) (Box 26)
    - General, 1980-1993 (Box 26)
    - Health, 1977-1991 (Box 26)
    - History (Ancient), 1974-1985 (Box 26)
    - Media, 1975-1995 (Box 26)
    - Politics, 1971-1991, (10 folders) (Box 26)
    - Politics (Box 27)
      - 1992-1994, (4 folders) (Box 27)
      - Charte Nationale, 1976 (Box 27)
      - Human Rights, 1990-1994 (Box 27)
      - Islamic Salvation Front (Box 27)
        - 1989-1994, (3 folders) (Box 27)
        - (GIA) Armed Islamic Group (Box 27)
        - GIA and other Fundamental Groups (Box 27)
      - Riots, 1988, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Reference, 1976-1992, (2 folders) (Box 27)
    - Religion, 1977-1994 (Box 27)